<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research | Academic</title>
    <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/tag/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jandrejevic12.github.io/tag/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/tag/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational modeling of crumpling dynamics</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my current research, I have been developing a large-scale simulation of thin, elastoplastic sheets to aid our study and analysis of crumpling dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popular model for elastic materials is a mass-spring system: a collection of discrete nodes that interact with their neighbors via linear springs. This simple framework can accurately reproduce continuum elastic properties of the material.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/crumpling_sim/mass_spring_model_hu8b814f376e16fa40746302a2d0f11dce_822428_d7477de3b3547e64780ad5035c4fee71.png 400w,
               /project/crumpling_sim/mass_spring_model_hu8b814f376e16fa40746302a2d0f11dce_822428_e4d5d25cb2b51b0089cbdbdf0bfd2f83.png 760w,
               /project/crumpling_sim/mass_spring_model_hu8b814f376e16fa40746302a2d0f11dce_822428_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/mass_spring_model_hu8b814f376e16fa40746302a2d0f11dce_822428_d7477de3b3547e64780ad5035c4fee71.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;225&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our work, we build on the widely-used elastic membrane model of Seung and Nelson&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and extend it to simulate self-avoiding, elastoplastic sheets. A key consideration in our implementation is the numerical procedure used to integrate the equations of motion for the sheet. We recognize that a sheet undergoing crumpling exhibits deformations on two different timescales: a slower timescale for wide-range smooth deformation, and a faster timescale for rapid buckling and local changes in velocity. This motivates two different formulations of the equations of motion: a quasistatic formulation in which acceleration is approximated as zero, and a dynamic formulation that retains acceleration as non-negligible. The quasistatic formulation may be efficiently integrated using an implicit scheme, while the dynamic formulation is handled explicitly. The complete model is implemented in C++ and multithreaded using OpenMP, and a paper for this work is currently in preparation.&lt;/p&gt;









  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/radial_crumple.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video above demonstrates one example simulation of a thin sheet radially confined into a ball. The sheet is modeled by 46767 nodes and 92716 triangles distributed randomly in a square domain. The sheet is compressed by a radial potential that mimics a spherical shell with decreasing radius. Short-range repulsive forces enforce the sheet’s self-avoidance, and plastic damage accumulates as regions of the sheet develop a large enough local curvature. Particularly interesting is the observation of individual snap-throughs of flat surfaces as the sheet locks in creases. The cross-sectional view midway through the video also reveals a high degree of layering of the sheet. After compressing for a time, the radius of the enclosing shell begins to increase, allowing the crumpled sheet to relax. At the end, the relaxed state of the sheet displays permanent plastic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seung, Hyunjune Sebastian, and David R. Nelson. &amp;ldquo;Defects in flexible membranes with crystalline order.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Physical Review A&lt;/em&gt; 38.2 (1988): 1005.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical properties of crumpled sheets</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/fragmentation_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/fragmentation_model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A key aspect of my research has been to better understand the statistical properties of crumpled sheets, as well as the mechanisms that can produce these statistics. As a familiar example, consider the process of crumpling a sheet of paper into a ball. Upon opening the sheet, we observe a complex network of creases where stresses sharply focused during compaction, introducing permanent, plastic deformation. We might ask how the amount of damage introduced varies with the strength of compaction, or how it is distributed spatially across the sheet.&lt;/p&gt;









  





&lt;video autoplay loop  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/fragmentation_model/unfold.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crumpling is a ubiquitous phenomenon that can be observed on many different length scales, from the scale of graphene membranes up to the deformation of the earth’s crust. And while crumpling might seem an unwelcome deformation at first glance, the properties of crumpled structures can offer a number of practical advantages due to their porosity, compression-resistance, shapeability, and lightweight nature. For instance, one exciting application of crumpling is in the context of batteries and supercapacitors: Crumpled graphene electrodes are shown to have higher electrochemical surface area and resistance to aggregation owing to the high porosity and rigidity of the crumpled state&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a scientific perspective, crumpling has garnered wide interest due to surprisingly predictable behavior that can be observed amidst this very disordered process. Let&amp;rsquo;s consider the simple crumpled ball experiment once again. If we crumple the same unfolded sheet a second time, new creases will develop; however, we expect the sheet to accumulate less additional damage, as it can exploit some of its existing creases during crumpling. A natural question we might ask is whether there is a rule for how such damage accumulates under repeated loading. Building on this idea, the experimental research group of Prof. Shmuel Rubinstein conducted studies of systematic crumpling by compressing a rolled sheet of Mylar with a cylindrical piston to a fixed compaction ratio, unfolding the sheet, and repeating the process. They discovered that when the total crease length accumulated is viewed as a function of crumpling iterations, the growth follows a simple logarithm&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\ell(n,\tilde{\Delta}) = c_1\left(1-\tilde{\Delta}\right)\log\left(1+c_2\frac{n}{\tilde{\Delta}}\right).$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the equation above, $\ell$ denotes total crease length, $n$ the number of crumpling iterations, and $\tilde{\Delta}$ the compaction ratio, which is the ratio of final to initial height of the piston. $c_1$ and $c_2$ are global fitting parameters. Surprisingly, this trend was robust to varying compaction ratio and initial preparations of the sheet, including pre-folding or hand-crumpling the sheet before repeated compaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logarithmic scaling was a remarkable reduction of complexity in characterizing crumpling. However, a physical justification for this mathematical model was missing: Can we explain why a logarithmic relationship, in particular, arises from this process? This question motivated our follow-up work to try and explain the origin of logarithmic growth on physical grounds&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We began by recognizing that as a sheet accumulates more creases over time, its surface area remains constant. Thus, rather than observing a quantity that continues to grow over time - the total crease length - we could instead look at a complementary quantity that remains invariant - the sum of individual facet areas. We found it valuable to perform the facet segmentations by hand, to ensure even the smallest facets were identified, and imaging artifacts such as faint or disconnected creases could be corrected. The facet segmentations then allowed us to observe the facet size distribution of each sheet, as well as its evolution over a series of crumples.&lt;/p&gt;









  





&lt;video autoplay loop  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/fragmentation_model/segmentation.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observed that these characteristic size distributions could be accurately explained by fragmentation theory, which has a rich history in modeling natural breakup phenomena such as the crushing of rock or fragmentation of volcanic debris. Fragmentation processes can be represented by an integro-differential equation that captures the evolution of the fragment size distribution over time as follows&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\frac{\partial{c(x,t)}}{\partial{t}}=-r(x)c(x,t) + \int_x^{\infty}r(y)c(y,t)f(x|y)dy.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the equation above, $c(x,t)$ represents the number or concentration of fragments with size $x$ at time $t$, and $r(x)$ and $f(x|y)$ are the overall breakup rate and conditional breakup probability, respectively. With appropriate choices of $r(x)$ and $f(x|y)$ inferred from experimental data, the above equation can be solved exactly, with $c(x,t)$ in agreement with the observed facet size distributions. Building on the fragmentation theory framework, we likewise introduced a model for how the accumulation of damage slows down over repeated crumpling, as the average facet size becomes smaller. This allowed us to explain the logarithmic scaling seen in experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application of fragmentation theory to understand crumpling is compelling, as it offers a new perspective on a well-studied system while drawing connections to other disordered processes. Future work could explore the extent to which fragmentation theory can more broadly model damage and failure in other systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about this project, please see the relevant publications:







  
    








  
  


  




&lt;div class=&#34;view-list-item&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s42005-018-0072-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A state variable for crumpled thin sheets&lt;/a&gt;

  

  

  
  &lt;div class=&#34;btn-links&#34;&gt;
    








  





&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/comm_phys_2018/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/a&gt;













&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1038/s42005-018-0072-x&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

  









  
    








  
  


  




&lt;div class=&#34;view-list-item&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;far fa-file-alt pub-icon&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21625-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;A model for the fragmentation kinetics of crumpled thin sheets&lt;/a&gt;

  

  

  
  &lt;div class=&#34;btn-links&#34;&gt;
    








  





&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm js-cite-modal&#34;
        data-filename=&#34;/publication/nat_commun_2021/cite.bib&#34;&gt;
  Cite
&lt;/a&gt;













&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header btn-sm&#34; href=&#34;https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21625-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  DOI
&lt;/a&gt;



  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

  

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was also featured in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/08/science/math-crumple-fragmentation-andrejevic.html#:~:text=From%20studies%20of%20%E2%80%9Cgeometric%20frustration,how%20paper%20folds%20under%20pressure.&amp;amp;text=Sign%20up%20for%20Science%20Times,cosmos%20and%20the%20human%20body.&amp;amp;text=can%27t%20sympathize%3F-,In%20a%20sense%2C%20creases%20happen%20when%20a,sheet%20of%20material%20gets%20claustrophobia.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Latest Wrinkle in Crumple Theory - &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seas.harvard.edu/news/2021/03/rock-paper-crumple&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rock, Paper, Crumple! - &lt;em&gt;Harvard SEAS News&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.howstuffworks.com/crumple-theory.htm#:~:text=Crumple%20Theory%3A%20We%20Can%20Learn%20a%20Lot%20From%20How%20Paper%20Crumples,-By%3A%20Patrick%20J&amp;amp;text=They%27re%20all%20undergoing%20a,fit%20into%20a%20smaller%20area.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crumple Theory: We Can Learn a Lot From How Paper Crumples - &lt;em&gt;HowStuffWorks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.harvardmagazine.com/2021/07/right-now-crumpled-paper&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How Paper Crumples - &lt;em&gt;Harvard Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.byuradio.org/08a94ba5-9a5f-4010-b057-95b6fcc31a91&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Crumple Theory: Top of Mind with Julie Rose, Episode 1576 - &lt;em&gt;BYU Radio&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luo, Jiayan, et al. &amp;ldquo;Compression and aggregation-resistant particles of crumpled soft sheets.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;ACS Nano&lt;/em&gt; 5.11 (2011): 8943-8949.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gottesman, Omer, et al. &amp;ldquo;A state variable for crumpled thin sheets.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Communications Physics&lt;/em&gt; 1.1 (2018): 1-7.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrejevic, Jovana, et al. &amp;ldquo;A model for the fragmentation kinetics of crumpled thin sheets.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt; 12.1 (2021): 1-10.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheng, Z., and S. Redner. &amp;ldquo;Kinetics of fragmentation.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and General&lt;/em&gt; 23.7 (1990): 1233.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
