<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching | Academic</title>
    <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/teaching/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jandrejevic12.github.io/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Teaching</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/teaching/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Experience</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/teaching/teaching_summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/teaching/teaching_summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;at-a-glance&#34;&gt;At a Glance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teaching experience during graduate studies at Harvard University has included assisting undergraduate and graduate level courses, developing a student-led mini-course, as well as formal training in effective pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I served as Teaching Fellow for the following courses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applied Physics 50A - Physics as a Foundation for Science and Engineering I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applied Physics 50B - Physics as a Foundation for Science and Engineering II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineering Sciences 301 - SEAS Teaching Practicum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applied Math 205 - Advanced Scientific Computing: Numerical Methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teaching philosophy statement is &lt;a href=&#34;uploads/teaching_statement.pdf&#34;&gt;available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graduate-teaching-experience&#34;&gt;Graduate Teaching Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a second-year graduate student, I had the opportunity to work with Prof. Eric Mazur and teach undergraduate physics in a nontraditional setting that emphasizes peer instruction and active learning. As a Teaching Fellow, my role included co-facilitating a weekly lab section, holding office hours and grading homework, as well as mentoring student groups on two long-term projects each semester. Teaching in a nontraditional setting was pivotal to my own development as an educator and helped me formulate the core teaching values I hope to exemplify in my academic career, which can be found in my &lt;a href=&#34;uploads/teaching_statement.pdf&#34;&gt;teaching statement&lt;/a&gt;. In 2018 and 2019, I was awarded the White Teaching Prize for excellence in teaching undergraduate physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall semesters of 2020 and 2021, I served as a Teaching Fellow for Advanced Scientific Computing: Numerical Methods, a graduate-level course taught by Prof. Chris Rycroft that introduces the fundamentals of scientific computing, from data-fitting and optimization to numerical calculus and solutions to systems of differential equations. In addition to holding office hours and grading problem sets, I prepared and led three lessons as part of a groupwork component of the course, and designed accompanying exercises that were completed in groups. Each semester, I closely mentored several student groups on their final projects, providing guidance on their initial proposal, and holding check-ins and advice throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching at Harvard has cultivated my passion for the science of teaching and effective classroom practices as well. As a fourth-year student, I trained as a Pedagogy Fellow through Harvard’s Derek Bok Center for Teaching and Learning. During this year-long position, I delved into active research topics in science education, attending weekly lessons, as well as participating in and facilitating a pedagogy journal club in the engineering department. I also mentored new graduate Teaching Fellows in their roles by holding microteaching practice sessions, observing lectures or office hours, and holding one-on-one consultations. Finally, I served as Teaching Fellow for the SEAS Teaching Practicum taught by John Girash, a course emphasizing hands-on teaching practice including lesson planning, developing problem sets, giving feedback, and communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January of 2020, I helped to design and co-facilitate a winter workshop on the topic of generative art at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology along with three fellow PhD students: Nina Andrejevic, George Varnavides, and Amina Matt. The course emphasized mathematical and natural examples of pattern formation such as fractals, cellular automata, swarming and self-organization, and emergent structure in reaction-diffusion processes. Due to high interest the following year, we resumed in virtual format in 2021, and thoroughly reworked the course material to adapt it to this new setting. We focused on tailoring our code examples to be highly interactive, built in group activities, and developed open-ended design challenges for the students to build upon class examples and showcase their creativity. Developing and leading this course, set to resume in 2022, has been an invaluable opportunity to synthesize the training and practice I&amp;rsquo;ve received. Further details on the workshop can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/#projects&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
