<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Academic</title>
    <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational modeling of crumpling dynamics</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my current research with Prof. Chris Rycroft, I have been developing a large-scale simulation of thin, elastoplastic sheets to aid our study and analysis of crumpling dynamics. The simulation is implemented in C++ and multithreaded using OpenMP. Specific components of the numerical implementation will be discussed separately; the video below demonstrates one example simulation of a thin sheet radially confined into a ball.&lt;/p&gt;









  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/crumpling_sim/radial_crumple.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheet is modeled as a triangulated lattice of discrete nodes which interact with their neighbors via stretching, bending, and damping forces. The example shown consists of 46767 nodes and 92716 triangles distributed randomly in a square domain. The sheet is compressed by a radial potential that mimics a spherical shell with decreasing radius. Short-range repulsive forces enforce the sheet’s self-avoidance, and plastic damage accumulates as regions of the sheet develop a large enough local curvature. Particularly interesting is the observation of individual snap-throughs of flat surfaces as the sheet locks in creases. The cross-sectional view midway through the video also reveals a high degree of layering of the sheet. After compressing for a time, the radius of the enclosing shell begins to increase, allowing the crumpled sheet to relax. The relaxed state of the sheet displays permanent plastic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principal component analysis with van Gogh</title>
      <link>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/pca_van_gogh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jandrejevic12.github.io/project/pca_van_gogh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project uses a collection of van Gogh&amp;rsquo;s paintings to shed light on a versatile tool in data science: principal component analysis. A hallmark of van Gogh&amp;rsquo;s Impressionist style was its rendition of only the essential features of his subjects, favoring simpler representations accomplished with broad brush strokes and bold color palettes. In turn, principal component analysis can be thought of as a view through van Gogh&amp;rsquo;s eyes: By reducing a collection of data only to those essential features which capture the greatest variability across the dataset, it provides a simpler representation of high-dimensional data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please check out the Github repository for a detailed description of the project! In 2019, it was awarded first place in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/view/harvard-data-science-animation/home&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harvard Data Science Animation Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
